[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
well tonight is our last class for this
quarter and I am NOT going to have time
to do all the things that I would have
liked to do what I'm going to do is show
you where the what I will do is tell you
where the basic things of
electrodynamics come from you can go
home you have enough information you can
go home and work out the equations by
yourself I will try to sort of outline
clearly where the various components
come from and where they go the basic
principle is always the principle of
least action but in order to use it you
have to know what the action is the
action is typically an integral of a
Lagrange density over all space-time so
before I do anything else let me just
remind you if you have a Lagrangian and
Lagrangian is composed of some
collection of fields let's just call a
generic collection of fields I don't
want to use Phi because so let's so
what's a good F F F F stands for field
and there may be a whole bunch of them
so let's label them F sub a a now is not
a space time index it doesn't refer to
dimension it just could be the first
field the second field the third field
it could run over fields a very
different type for example as a varied
one-one F might be a scalar field
another F might be a vector field like
the vector potential so this is very
generic a collection of fields which
depend on X and T or in a relativistic
notation they would depend just on the
four components of space-time the
Lagrangian in general is a function of
the F all of the FS
they're first derivatives with respect
to the exes so the Lagrangian the
Lagrangian s'ti is a function which
depends on the derivatives of F with
respect to the various directions there
are four of them for each a F a so this
notation is just meant to indicate that
the Lagrangian can depend on all of the
first derivatives of any one of the
fields F and also the undifferentiated
fields F also for example in the scalar
field lagrangian that we studied the
Lagrangian was the sums of squares or
differences of squares of the
derivatives of F with respect to X and
then we also threw in another one
another term which I call the mass term
which just depended on the field itself
without derivatives so this is the
general form the action is the integral
of this thing over all space-time but
just as for a single particle when you
think about a single particle and you
ask what the implications of the
principle of least action are you can
either think about the whole thing
globally or you can just think locally
and you can say what implications are
there for what are going on in the
vicinity of a point what are the
implications of the principle of least
action and the answer is oiler Lagrange
differential equations which you would
call field equations for a field I'm not
going to derive them I'm just going to
write down with the general form is
before I do let me write down the form
the ordinary form of the Euler Lagrange
equations for the motion of a particle
if you have a particle with a set of or
a set of particles instead of having F a
we will have a set of coordinates X a
and the Lagrangian would be a function
this would be now it's not the
Lagrangian would be a function of L of
the time derivative of X that's the
velocity and the X's themselves okay so
the Lagrangian in this case is a
function also of derivatives now a
fields not coordinate positions of
particles and also the field itself
undifferentiated it's similar to this
that blue board is a generalization of
this board in which there are no is not
one independent variable that a
coordinate can depend on but four
independent variables that the that a
field can depend on okay let me just
remind you what the Euler Lagrange
equations are they say first
differentiate Lagrangian no I better
call this square Lagrangian L with
respect to the velocity of the eighth
coordinate not eighth as in one two
three four five six seven eight but
eighth as in little a you take the
Lagrangian and you differentiate it with
respect to the derivative of the
coordinate in this case there's only
time derivatives then you differentiate
that with respect to time that's the
left-hand side of the Euler Lagrange
equation that follows from the principle
of this action least action and the
right-hand side is just the derivative
of the Lagrangian with respect to X a
how many such equations are there this
one oops this should be X sub a there's
one such equation for each value of
little a so if there are a hundred
coordinates then there are a hundred
equations and of course these equations
are nothing but Newton's equations for
the several coordinates describing the
particles in the system the analogue on
this side is very similar this time you
have a set of derivatives not just a
time derivative but also space
derivatives the first thing you do is
differentiate the Lagrangian with
respect to the derivatives that appear
in it
now can you differentiate something with
respect to a derivative you bet you can
we just differentiated the Lagrangian
with respect to a time derivative in the
same way we can differentiate the
Lagrangian s'ti with respect to what it
depends on which is the partial
derivative of F a with respect to X mu
there are several such derivatives and
so there are several terms like this for
each a we're focusing now on one value
of a just as we focused on one value of
a over here that's the first thing it's
the analogue of the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to the velocity
then we have to differentiate that not
with respect to T in general but with
respect to X mu itself so we
differentiate that with respect to X mu
now this left-hand side for each a is
really a sum of four terms let me write
it out explicitly or almost explicitly
it's the derivative with respect to time
which I'll call X naught of the
derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to the time derivative of f AE
this is the time derivative of FA this
we could have also called this D by DT
of the derivative the Lagrangian with
respect to F dot in other words the
analog of this but then there were more
terms
there is also remember the Einstein
summation convention
whenever you see a repeated space-time
index like that it means you sum over it
so there's also derivative with respect
to X one of the same kind of thing
derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to derivative of F with respect
to X 1 and so forth and so on
for the other two coordinates that's the
structure of the left-hand side of the
Euler Lagrange equations the right-hand
side we just differentiate the
Lagrangian with respect to F a so that's
equals the derivative of the Lagrangian
density with respect to the field itself
yeah there that's belong don't they this
is of the form typically this is a wave
equation it's typically a wave equation
if you work it out for the little scalar
field Lagrangian that we've worried that
we've worked out several times you'll
find out this is just the good old wave
equation for the motion of an ordinary
waves
it's the analog of this and having said
it now let's put it up here that's the
way we derive equations of motion
differential equations from the
principle of least action
what equations are we interested in
we're interested in Maxwell's equations
we've already worked out the equations
of motion of a scalar field let's come
now to Maxwell's equations let me just
write down what they are
there are various there are plenty of
different notation and conventions and
units I'm going to write them down in a
sort of unit free way where I have these
perfectly good units I forget which ones
they are where all the four PI's don't
appear in the equations they appear
someplace else they do appear they
appear in the solutions of equations
various constants associated what is it
called mu and epsilon they're all set
equal to one there are they called
rationalized units I always forget but
here they are his Maxwell's equations
hmm yeah it is rational all right one of
the equations for the equations are for
the electric and magnetic field all
right the electric and magnetic fields
are fields obviously they depend on
space how many of them are there
altogether six three components of the
electric field three components of the
magnetic field the electric field is e
the magnetic field is B I have no idea
what the history of beef and magnetic
field is I don't know why it wasn't
called
em I don't know hmm yeah I suppose it
was mass so I don't know why but we're
stuck with it the last the last lecture
we spent some time you know adding a
term to the partial to show how to
restore gauging yes we're going to talk
about that more right we're going to
talk but I wanted here's the target the
target is what you want to get and then
we're going to go back through a grungy
in and the in variances and all that
stuff and see how we would go about
getting this from the principles
Lagrangian Euler Lagrange equations
should produce Maxwell's equations and I
just just a regular partial up there
it's not doesn't know gauge term added
to
mr. where oh never mind this these
things could involve the gauge fields I
mean that's very general all right okay
incidentally the electric and magnetic
fields are not the fundamental fields
like fa in this formula the electric and
magnetic fields are more like the
derivatives of the fundamental fields
with respect to the coordinates but
we'll see why anyway here's what we want
to get to everybody remember Maxwell's
equations
I remember them up to a sign all right
divergence of the electric field
everybody anybody not know what a
divergence is good then I don't have to
write down little divergences the
divergence of the electric field this is
of course derivative with respect to X
of the X component of the electric field
plus derivative with respect to Y of the
Y component etc all right three terms
that's equal to what throw the charge
density and some people's some people's
version there's a 4pi in there in mind
there is no 4pi anyway
del dot E is equal to Rho the curl of e
everybody know what a curl is know who
let who said no out I do you mean it oh
there she likes but she explained or hmm
you do it don't know somebody said no
but I couldn't hear where was all right
I will tell you what the curl of a
vector field is but we'll have to do it
fast because uh all right anytime you
see the upside-down triangle that means
it's a derivative of some sort okay
you did you said you didn't know what
divergence is yes or no if not I will
write it down okay
if you have a vector field in this case
a vector now means a three-dimensional
vector that has three components let's
call them let's be very very specific
now XY and Z the X component the
electric field the Y component of the
electric field and the Z component
alright the divergence of the electric
field is the measure
remember the vector field is a vector at
every point in space and so at every
point in space it points in some
direction and the divergence is a
measure of the spreading of the electric
field away from a point for example a
typical
vector field that has a divergence would
point away from some point like that
it's diverging that's all right now the
the mathematical expression that
represents this tendency of the vector
field to point away from a point like
that is called the divergence at Dell
dot e that's it that's the notation for
it and it stands for the derivative of
the X component with respect to X plus
the derivative of the Y component with
respect to Y plus the derivative of the
Z component with respect to Z definition
but it does have this property that it
tends to show you that something is
spreading away from a point of course
yeah okay that's the notion of
divergence
now there's another notion called curl
which is also a kind of geometric notion
it tells you if you take an axis now a
3-dimensional axis this is a
three-dimensional ideas when spreading
away from a point is a three-dimensional
notion spreading away in all three
directions the curl is also a
three-dimensional Neurath notion but it
itself is a vector the curl itself has
three components
all right and it is each component is
related to an axis and what the curl is
is given an axis let's say the axis out
of the blackboard it represents the
tendency of the vector field to sort of
wind around that direction it's um if we
thought of wind velocity as the relevant
field then a tornado would have a large
curl right at the center of the tornado
the velocity field the wind velocity
would be circulating around a point a
hurricane would have a a large sometimes
it's called vorticity but curls is the
right term and I'm going to write down
what the formula is so let's take let's
call this axis the z axis no let's call
that axis yeah
let's call a z axis then the symbol for
the curl is del cross e it's related to
the concept of cross product and I'm not
going to go through cross product today
but I'm going to assume you know what it
is but in this particular case I'll
write down exactly what it is it has in
its itself it has three components so
let's take the Z component of it Z
component and this is the thing which
represents the tendency of the field to
wrap around or to circulate around the z
axis obviously we could also think about
the tendency to circulate around the x
axis or the y axis that's why this three
components and this is given by the X
derivative of the Y component minus the
y derivative of the X component that's
the Z component of the curl and as I
said it represents the tendency of the
field to wrap around that direction like
that
and now if you want to go to the other
two components of
it you just cycle through Z cycle in the
following sense X Y Z X goes to Y Y goes
to Z Z goes back to X so here's what I
mean by that you go to the next equation
by substituting for Z X for X Y and for
y back to Z so here's what it would look
like del cross e ID Z cycles 2x so put
an X there is equal now X goes to Y so
that's derivative with respect to Y y
goes to Z minus DZ e Y and what would be
next you cycle once more through the
three letters of the alphabet del cross
e the Y component Z X Y is equal X Y the
next one will be Z Y Z next is X and
minus the x ey sorry DX e Z these are
the three components of a curl so this
is an operation that you do on a vector
and gives you another vector this is an
operation that you do on a vector and
gives you a scalar alright one of them
gives you the tendency the for the field
to separate out from a point it's a
scalar the divergence and the other has
three components the circulation of the
field around the three axes basically
okay now Maxwell's first equation is Del
dot e equals Rho this is the equation
that tells you that charge densities
make electric fields for example it's at
the root of the fact that if you have a
point electric charge if you have a
point electric charge an electric field
radiates out from it so what it says is
that the alais is that the charge
is a divergence of the electric field
now the corresponding equation for the
magnetic field is Del dot B and what you
might think you should put on the
right-hand side is some density of
magnetic charge
what does magnetic charge mean it would
mean a little particle which we call a
magnetic monopole a magnetic monopole
would be a particle that the field
magnetic field lines would radiate out
of there are no known particles like
that in nature although every physicist
of my particular persuasion meaning my
particular subject rather than my
particular belief system almost all
theoretical physicists engaged in the
subject of particle physics and so forth
believed that magnetic monopoles really
do exist just to see what's involved
imagine a bar magnet a bar magnet has a
North Pole and a South Pole and out of
the North Pole comes magnetic field
lines and the magnetic field lines look
something like this you've all seen this
you take a magnet magnet put it under a
piece of paper sprinkle some iron
filings on it and you make something
like this now if you take the South Pole
very very far away extremely far away
and you look just at the North Pole what
you would see let's take that South Pole
and bring it to Australia way off a
blackboard what you would see in the
vicinity of the North Pole would look
very much like the field of
an electron or a charged particle except
that of course it would not be an
electric field it would be a magnetic
field magnetic field radiating Oh out
away from the North Pole so you might
think the North Pole then is the
divergent or the North Pole is behaving
like the divergence of the magnetic
field but if you look more carefully
what you'll find is that there's also a
magnetic field running right through the
magnet right through the the magnet like
that and then in fact the magnetic field
is coming in here in other words the
magnetic field lines run right through
the magnet and then radiate out away
from the from the North Pole there
really is no divergence to the magnetic
field what comes in goes out so it
really doesn't have a divergence like
the electric field does the electric
field really does radiate out away from
an electron this magnetic divergence
here is just because we didn't look
inside the the magnet there are no known
sources of magnetic field which are
point sources in the sense that the
field radiates out away from them in all
possible directions here in and out so
the divergence of the magnetic field is
zero magnetic fields don't have
divergences at least not until somebody
discovers a magnetic monopole now you
can fool your friends you can get
yourself a very very thin magnet another
thing which were there's another thing
which will make a magnetic field a
solenoid if instead of a magnet you make
an electromagnet in other words you just
wrap wire around the an axis like this
and let current go through it then the
magnetic field lines go through the
solenoid and out the end here now you
make yourself an extremely thin flexible
solenoid
and you grab ahold of this end then you
bring it to your friends and you say
look I have a magnetic monopole yeah you
can fool your friends into thinking you
have a magnetic monopole if you could
have a solenoid which was so thin that
it could pass between atoms and so forth
that's actually what a magnetic monopole
is it's a magnetic charge which is some
mathematical sense really connected to
an infinitely thin infinitely light
infinitely flexible solenoid but in
until somebody discovers a real magnetic
monopole the right-hand side of this
equation is zero all right now we also
have equations for the curl of the
electric field the curl of the electric
field now what's the curl of the
electric field equal to the time
derivative of the magnetic field this
says that a changing magnetic field if
the magnetic field in space changes it
necessarily creates an electric field if
B dot is not zero in other words if a
magnetic field is changing with time
it creates an electric field for example
supposing we started let's take a
solenoid but let's make it infinitely
long in both directions I'm not
particularly interested now in this
monopole problem we take them out of the
solenoid infinitely long we start with
no current in the solenoid so there's no
magnetic field then we start increasing
the magnetic field sorry yes we start
increasing the current increasing the
current creates a magnetic field through
them through the solenoid as we increase
the current the magnetic field increases
and for that reason it generates an
electric field the electric field has a
curl so it wraps around what does it
wrap around
it wraps around the solenoid so ramping
up the current through a solenoid
creates an electric field around the
solenoid and in fact in particular that
electric field could accelerate a
charged particle and yet moving in a
circle all right that's the meaning of
this equation whose law is this that a
changing magnetic field that makes an
electric field always forget that's all
of parody knew it I'm not sure the can
remember which one is which okay that's
the that's the magnetic field making
electric field and there's a similar
equation for the magnetic field the curl
of a magnetic field is related to the
time derivative of the electric field
minus sign in this case a minus sign
electric field dot so this says a
changing electric field will also make a
magnetic field for example you take a
capacitor plates capacitor plates over
here connected the wires if the
capacitor plate if the capacitor plates
have charge on them then there will be
an electric field between the capacitor
plates now we can start with an
uncharged capacitor and pump some
electric charge into the capacitor
plates and so in that way ramp up the
electric field ramping up the electric
field must make a magnetic field and in
fact the magnetic field has to wrap
around something it wraps around the
direction of the electric field lines
all right so ramping up the the charge
and a capacitor temporarily creates a
magnetic field and that magnetic field
would orient the a compass so a compass
would respond to a changing a changing
electric field in this manner here
this is not the complete equation
there's another thing on the right hand
side oh is it the current the current
not the charge density but the current
the current density J both sides of this
equation in fact both sides of this
equation are vectors the curl of the
electric field is a vector the magnetic
field is a vector the curl of the
magnetic field is a vector the electric
field and its time derivative are also
vectors and the current is a vector now
this is the three-dimensional current
remember what let me just remind you
what that current means the
three-dimensional current if you take a
little window in space oriented so that
the perpendicular to it is along some
axis then the amount of charge passing
through the little window per unit time
per unit area is called the component of
J in that direction so it's the electric
charge passing through a little window
in space per unit time per unit space
and the reason it's a vector is because
you can orient that little window in
different directions and in that way
sample the current going in different
directions all right so that's J and
that's on the right-hand side know what
that says is how do you get how do you
get current I'm sorry how do you get
charged to get onto these capacitor
plates well there's only one way and
that's to send a current into them right
so you have to send an electric current
into here that will charge up the
capacitor plates and during the time
that that the capacitor plate is being
charged there is a current in here that
current even in places let's say far
away from where the electric field is
from the capacitor plates let's go way
out here
there's an electric current going
through here and that electric current
also makes a magnetic field which
windings around
here like that so it's kind of
interesting here's the picture you can
have an interrupted place where the
current cannot flow and in that way make
a capacitor plate like this make the
capacitor very long the flow of current
as its ramping up the capacitor makes
magnetic field lines which wrap around
the the wire but it doesn't stop at the
place where the current ends it
continues the the magnetic field
continues into the region in the gap
here and it continues because the
right-hand side contains both the time
derivative of electric field as well as
the current this term has a incidentally
Faraday didn't know about this term he
only knew about this he knew that a
current makes a magnetic field okay
Maxwell realized actually that there was
an EM not an ambiguity and inconsistency
in the equations without this term here
and Maxwell put that term in it's called
the displacement current I don't know
who's being displaced I think that one
is amperes law yeah that is right where
the J it's closed amp ere's law and we
did okay this is called as displacement
curve okay according to this just let
the sign of V and
backwards always happens now am I better
of course that can be absorbed into a
change of definition very easily but
look if you change the sign the
definition of the sign of the magnetic
field that won't change this equation
it'll change this one and change its
sign it'll change this one and change
its sign and then if you and you can
change J by changing the definition of
which is positive and which is negative
electric charge so there's no real
there's no real content in yeah yeah
that's right that's right so the signs
there are conventions but once you fix
them you fix them who was it that fixed
the convention about positive and
negative charge Benjamin Franklin yeah
because he had no way of knowing what it
was that was actually flowing in the
wires there was no way that he could
know that the electron was the
fundamental charge carrier he called the
current negative meaning to say a flow
of electrons in a certain direction
he called arbitrarily a negative flow of
current and the result of that has been
hundreds of years of confusion among the
yeah I have to explain this every time I
teach elementary electromagnetism I have
to explain and it drives everybody crazy
that a flow of electrons this way
corresponds to a current that way Ben
Franklin did some good things but that
wasn't one of them okay now well we want
to try to get these equations oh there's
one more equation which is central to
electrodynamics these equations tell you
how the charges and currents the charge
and the flow
of charge create or effect the
electromagnetic field the other side of
the coin is the way the electromagnetic
field affects the charges and it affects
the charges by exerting forces on them
so the other side of the coin is the
force exerted on a charged object due to
the electromagnetic field all right so
let me write down what that force is
it's called the Lorentz force law and
it's the force on a charged particle is
equal first of all there's the electric
charge of the particle let's call that e
that for electric charge measured in
some units and our purpose now is not to
worry about units the measured in
coulombs and the charge of an electron
is a horribly small number of coulombs
what is it I don't remember what it is
hmm something like that
10 to the minus 19 coulombs for the
electron yeah so that's a very small
number but for an electron for for some
other object it may be of order 1 and
maybe bigger
incidentally 1 Coulomb of charge is a
huge amount of charge if you put one
Coulomb of charge on a basketball the
effect of the repulsion would just blast
it to the smithereens so a Coulomb of
charges a lot of charge but the force is
proportional to the charge on a particle
and then there's two terms one of them
is just the electric field the force is
proportional to the electric field the
factor of proportionality being the
electric charge so first of all in here
this is the electric field incidentally
both sides are vectors in the
three-dimensional sense
force and electric field then is another
term which is absent unless the electron
or the charge is moving so a stationary
electric charge this is all there is
then is a velocity dependent
force and it's plus the velocity of the
particle cross-product with the magnetic
field so it's proportional to the
product of velocity and magnetic field
it points in the direction perpendicular
to both the velocity and the magnetic
field so if we have a magnetic field
that's opposes a magnetic field pointing
into the blackboard magnetic field
pointing into the blackboard we usually
represent by by a bunch of little
crosses the idea I'm told is that
magnetic fields are arrows and looking
at the arrow from behind you see the
feathers so here's the feathers alright
if you want the magnetic field to come
toward you you just see the points of
the arrows I'm told that's where this
convention comes from so here's a
magnetic field pointing into the
blackboard V cross B if you don't know
what a cross-product is I'll rough it
out for you now but not with a
mathematical precision it's first of all
a vector which is proportional to the
velocity proportional to the magnetic
field and in the direction perpendicular
to both of them so for example
if it's proportional to the to the
electric and magnetic field it's also
proportional to the sine of the angle
between the electric and magnetic field
sorry between the velocity and a
magnetic field that's what a cross
product is so if the velocity is in the
same direction or opposite direction to
the magnetic field there is no force the
sine of the angle between the velocity
and the magnetic field is zero if the
charge is moving in this direction then
the force is perpendicular to both the
magnetic field and to the charge there's
only one direction that's perpendicular
to both of them and that would be the
vertical direction I can't tell is the
is it the upward or downward V cross B
upward
alright so apart
particle moving through here if it were
moving with a velocity V would have a
force on it which would bend it upward
the faster it moves the larger the force
the larger the magnetic field
larger the force that's this term this
is called the Lorentz force law electric
and magnetic forces this term is
velocity dependent this term is not
velocity dependent that's what we would
like to get out of a fundamental theory
of electromagnetism so what do we need
to do we need to find ourselves a
Lagrangian which when we subject it to
the principle of least action will give
us these one two three four or five
equations now how many equations are
there there's a lot more than that this
is one equation this is one equation one
equation one equation how many is this
this is three equations and this is
three equations so these are the field
equations that's one two six and two is
eight eight equations and hmm again
and three equations for the force law
yeah three equations for the force law
and we'd like to derive them from a
principle of least action-y among other
things it's the principle of least
action which guarantees that there's a
concept of energy if in the theory of
electromagnetic forces and
electromagnetic field there was not a
good concept of a conserved energy this
sure wouldn't be any concept of
conserved energy in the world because so
much of physics has to do with electric
and magnetic forces almost everything in
our electric magnetic and gravitational
and the only thing in the basic
principles of physics that guarantee
that there's a concept of energy and
momentum is the principle of least
action
and the formulation of mechanics and
field theory in terms of a Lagrangian so
it's not it's not just because it's
pretty or not just because we like ideas
like the principle of least action it is
really important to derive theories from
a principle of least action because if
you don't none of the rules about the
connection between symmetries and
conserved quantities make any sense
the connection between symmetries and
conserved quantities that includes
energy conservation momentum
conservation charge conservation all of
those things are dependent on the on the
principles of mechanics that are
embodied in the Lagrangian or in the
principle of least action okay so let's
let's try to invent a theory of
electricity and magnetism
assuming some basic principles two basic
principles really
I'm not sure in which order to write
them down so I'll write them down in the
order that we learned about these things
and they're quite independent the two
basic principles are first of all
Lorentz invariance in other words
Lorentz invariance in other words the
special theory of relativity it's all
this and this alone which guarantees for
example that the speed of light is the
same in every reference frame Lorentz
invariance includes rotational
invariance and so this is the basic
symmetry of space and time if you like
it also includes the idea that things
don't depend on the position that you do
the experiment if you translated
everything it would stay the same if you
rotated everything it would stay the
same if you subject it to a velocity
boost and examine a system from a moving
reference frame it should say it should
stay the same should same consequences
all right so Lorentz invariance is one
basic principle and Lorentz invariance
is very simple from the point of view of
the Lagrangian all you have to do is
make sure that the Lagrangian density is
a scalar that's all so it's easy right
so Lagrangian density should be a scalar
next a little less familiar but also not
very difficult is gauge invariance gauge
invariance gauge invariance let me
remind you about gauge invariance where
it came from was requiring that a
certain scalar field Lagrangian should
be invariant when we did this kind of
change of phase the e to the I epsilon
and that epsilon be a function of
position but let me remind you the
bottom line the end was the bottom line
in the end was that we had to invent in
order to in order to implement that
symmetry we had to invent the idea of a
get of a vector potential what we had to
do was replace the derivative of a
scalar field with respect to position
which is not invariant on the gauge
transformation if we multiply the scalar
field by e to the I epsilon of X then in
taking the derivative here there are
terms with a derivative of epsilon just
not invariant what do we have to do
anybody remember what we had to do in
order to to make the Lagrangian of the
scalar field gauge invariant right we
had to change from the ordinary
derivative to what is called the
covariant derivative right to add to
this plus i.e vector potential times phi
if at the same time that we multiply Phi
by e to the I epsilon X if at the same
time we transform a to a plus the
epsilon by DX and I think I should have
a 1 over electric charge there if we
change the vector potential in this way
whenever we do such a transformation
then this covariant derivative this
so-called covariant derivative doesn't
change its invariant so if we build a
Lagrangian instead of just out of d phi
by DX the covariant derivative this
incidentally is often represented as d
mu Phi if we build the Lagrangian not
wherever we originally saw the
derivative of Phi we write the covariant
derivative of Phi then the Lagrangian is
gauge invariant but that was the origin
of this idea of a vector potential the
vector potential is necessary to soak up
the change that would happen in the
ordinary derivative when we multiply by
e to the I epsilon of X
all right but having now that we have a
we can ask first of all what kind of
lagrangian's can we cook up which are
gauge invariant
what kind of LaGrange densities can we
cook up that a gauge invariant before we
do that we should ask what kind of
structures what kind of combinations can
we make that our gauge invariant and the
simplest answer the simplest thing that
we can make which is gauge invariant out
of a II what is a how many components is
a have four time component also this is
a four vector its fourth component its
time component is the electrostatic is
the electric potential is what's usually
called the potential but in any case
there are four components the three of
them the three space components are
often just called the vector potential
but in a relativistic setting all there
are four components to the vector
potential okay so a then has an index
which runs over the usual space-time
indices a itself is not gauge invariant
how do I know because it transforms it
changes when you do a gauge
transformation it goes to a plus
something so a is not gauge invariant
but to make a long story short the
simplest thing which is gauge invariant
is a tensor a thing with a thing with
two indices a mu index and a new index
and here it is you differentiate the
Meuse component of a with respect to the
knuth component of position this means
derivative for example this could
contain something like derivative of ax
with respect to Y the new would be
correspond to Y mu would correspond to X
there are also terms for time components
but let's just write down that's a thing
with two components it is a tensor but
we don't really need to know what a
tensor is for these purposes it is what
it is
the river to respect the new of a mule
now what happens to this object when you
subject a to such a transformation what
happens is it picks up an extra term so
let's look at it
here's a mule what about the derivative
of a mule with respect to X nu
what it does is it just goes to D nu mu
plus 1 over e and then the second
derivative of epsilon with respect to X
nu with respect to X mu the second
partial derivative with respect to Nu mu
this is the change that happens when you
do a gauge transformation through this
particular combination this is not gauge
invariant the changes but notice that
this change here is symmetric under the
interchange of mu and mu the process of
differentiation it doesn't matter which
order you differentiate process of
differentiation with respect to two
coordinates commute commute means it
doesn't matter which order you apply
those two operations and that means that
if I subtract from this minus D mu a new
this term will cancel why because this
term is symmetric when I interchange mu
and nu and so when I subtract the same
object with the opposite ordering immune
or the opposite dependence on mu and nu
this term will cancel the result is that
this object D mu a nu which is called f
mu nu that's gauge invariant that will
not change when you do a gauge
transformation
how many such objects are there how many
components does it have well offhand
mewhen new can run from 1 to 4 so it
looks like a 16 independent components
of F nu nu not so and the reason is that
this is anti-symmetric if you
interchange mu and nu it changes sign so
that means for example that F 1 2 is
just equal to minus F 2 1 F 1 3 is minus
F 3 1 so the different components of F
mu nu are not independent its
anti-symmetric how many components of an
anti-symmetric matrix are there in 4
dimensions all the diagonal components
are 0 in other words if I said if nu and
mu are the same these two terms will
cancel F 1 1 what is F 1 1 if F 1 1 is
equal to the derivative with respect to
x1 of a 1 minus the derivative with
respect to x1 of a 1 so 0 the diagonal
elements are all 0 and the off diagonal
elements have opposite sign when you
interchange the two the two indices so
how many of them are altogether
six-six-six independent you can think of
it as a matrix a 4 by 4 matrix 16 to
start with 0 on the diagonal and off
diagonal the off diagonal there are 6
off diagonal above the 6 over there and
another 6 over here but the other 6 over
here are just the negatives of the ones
over here so there are six independent
components and those six independent
components are nothing but the electric
and magnetic fields
the components of the electric magnetic
fields let me write them down for you we
start with F let's start with F 0 1 by
definition this is the derivative with
respect to X naught X naught is time so
it's just the time derivative of a 1 1
could stand for the X component so F
naught 1 would be derivative of a 1 with
respect to X naught minus the derivative
of a naught with respect to X 1 same
thing if I replace 1 by 2 and 3 so there
are 3 components which are the form F
naught X Y or Z those three components
form the electric field this is e 1 the
X component of the electric field would
be the derivative of the X component of
the vector potential with respect to
time minus the derivative of the time
component of the vector potential with
respect to X 1 with respect to X so
that's we have three components of the
electric field and now we also have
three additional components let me tell
you their connection with a magnetic
field that's a little this this one will
sort of obviate if not obvious easy the
other one is also not difficult
first of all f12
that's got to be that for example the XY
component let's use x and y now I'm only
interested in space components now and
the other three components do not
involve a time index why not well these
three involve the time index the only
thing out the other other thing that
could involve a time index would be F 0
0 there is no
zero so the other three components
involve pairs of space indices for
example F XY and I'm now using X for one
and Y for two just to be specific if XY
is equal to the derivative let's see
which way it works derivative with
respect to X of a Y minus the derivative
with respect to Y ax now the only thing
that's left is the components of the
magnetic field so this must be some
component of the magnetic field which
component of the magnetic field Z we
have a if by some sort of symmetry we uh
could it could only be the Z component
it is the Z component so this is the Z
component of the magnetic field and then
to get the other ones you just cycle
again X to Y Y to Z Z back to Y busy
back to X so f X F X Y Z that's equal to
be Y AZ minus DZ a Y and that's what
that's B what comes after Z X and the
last one F X Y Z Y Z X is equal to X Y Z
Y Z X minus dot dot dot and that's equal
to B Y so this is the connection between
this also says the curl of a another way
to write this is that curl of a is equal
to B alright so that's the that's the
other electric field involve a time
component and a space component they
also involve a time derivative but the
magnetic field never has a time
derivative in it it only has space
derivatives in it okay that's the that's
the electro
magnetic field tensor and the important
thing about it is that it's gauge
invariant in fact it's the simplest
thing that you can make up out of the
vector potential that is gauge invariant
how about this point arbitrary vector
well apart from smoothness and
differentiability right no no condition
on it in fact there's an ambiguity in
its definition because you can always do
a gauge transformation on it so it's
quite the free to vary in any way okay
now we want to build a Lagrangian
[Music]
lagrangian's typically involve fields
and their time derivatives are sorry
fields and their various derivatives the
field a by itself if undifferentiated is
not gauge invariant there's no way to
put into the Lagrangian the field
undifferentiated without destroying the
gauge invariance
a by itself is not gauge invariant you
can make the Lagrangian out of any
combination of the F's anything that
involves F is gauge invariant since F
itself is gauge invariant gauge
invariance is not enough to tell you
what combinations of F's to put together
in what form the other thing that goes
in is Lorentz invariance if we have F mu
nu in all our on Jian and we want to
make a scalar the simplest scalar that
we can make is just to multiply it by F
mu nu again and contract the indices in
the way that we've learned how to do
some Einstein summation convention
as long as the indices are contracted
contracted means just summed over when
they're repeated we make a scaler right
this is in fact a minus 1/4 but that's
mostly convention as a minus 1/4 but as
I said that that's simply a convention
and it plus whenever anybody puts a
minus 1/4 in a thing like this you know
that what it does is it remove the 4
from some later equation and it does it
removes force from Maxwell equations
there but it's it's it's arbitrary it
could be absorbed into changes of the
electric and magnetic field so it's not
important the important thing is that
it's gauge invariant because it's made
out of F and it's Lorentz invariant
because it's indices have been correctly
grouped and summed over
that's the Lagrangian of the
electromagnetic field okay Lagrangian
density and what is it let's write it
out one over for partial derivative of a
mu with respect to X no remember what
indices upstairs mean they mean exactly
the same thing as indices downstairs
except for the time component where you
change sign so for example if there's a
time component in either mu or nu then
if flip sign relative to the original
definition of F nu no so it's just a
question of signs whether the indices
are upstairs to downstairs minus D mu a
nu that's the field tensor with the
upstairs indices okay and we multiply it
are the field tensor or the downstairs
indices D mu do I have it right I think
I might have the you know I think I
should have mu and nu
knowing you
this stands for various squares and sums
of squares of various components of the
electric and magnetic field I'll write
it out in terms of the electric and
magnetic field at a moment but let me
just point out what it is it's a thing
which is quadratic in various
derivatives of the field in that respect
it's not so different than D mu Phi D mu
Phi it's quadratic in derivatives it's
more complicated because it has more
components but again each term is
something which is the product of a
derivative of a field times another
derivative of field so this is a
Lagrangian which involves quadratic
expressions in other words things which
are products of two field derivatives
summed in various ways so it's not so
different than then previous
lagrangian's that we've studied in the
case of the scalar field without
violating any symmetry with that I think
we had a star here for example in the
case of a complex field we were also
able to add M Squared Phi star Phi maybe
- there is nothing that we can add to
this that doesn't involve derivatives of
the field of something like adding a
square or something like that no good a
squared is not gauge invariant or mu a
mu you might think well why can't we add
a mule a mu so Lorentz invariant but
it's not gauge invariant it changes when
you let a go to a plus the derivative of
Epsilon so this is not gauge invariant
otherwise it's perfectly good Lorentz
invariant perfectly good perfectly
acceptable Lagrangian from every other
point of view but it's not gauge
invariant so this is the Lagrangian of
electrodynamics
let me tell you what it has in it let's
look at it it has various squares
various products of the components of F
what is it it's F mu nu F mu nu it's
proportional to sums of squares or
differences of squares depending on
which component we're talking about come
in with a plus sign or a minus sign for
example here's F naught 1 F naught 1 now
what is f naught 1 with lower index here
let me remember
you 1 or X what is it with the upper
index here when you raise a space
component index nothing happens when you
raise a time component index the sign
changes alright so this is proportional
to minus e x squared right there's a
minus CX squared well is another term
here which is f1 not f1 not but that's
exactly the same thing
why because f1 naught is just minus F
you know this is minus this this is
minus this the two terms here just
double this the dividing by four that
makes it divided by 2 and then the minus
here just changes it to plus so the
terms involving F naught 1 F naught 2 F
naught 3 they just give you the sums of
the squares of the electric field
components
ey squared plus EZ squared that's what's
in the Lagrangian from the mixed
space-time components what about the
space space components again minus 1/4
let's look at one of them
mixed Spade the space space components
could have f1 to f12 what is F 1 2 times
f1 to first of all what is F 1 2 its b3
b3
maybe it's minus b3 I don't remember but
we're squaring it so it doesn't matter
now here I've raised both indices one to
two spaces disease okay
so f1 to upper sings that one to
Banglore this is b3 squared there's a
minus of water so I get my support
increase where why is it my to have a
nice water so there's another term which
is 2 1 2 B 3 squared divided by 2 CN is
reading the DZ square plus C watch
[Music]
Ranjan century one all right so a
squared minus B squared a little bit
funny it's it involves the electric
field and magnetic field sort of almost
symmetrically but not quite one comes in
with a negative sign the other comes in
with a - it was a positive sign hmm
let's look at the electric field again
the electric field involves I'm going to
be a little sketchy right now because we
don't have time but nevertheless sketchy
or not the argument is correct the
electric field which is F naught 1 for
example contains things like derivative
with respect to X naught that means
derivative with respect to time times a
1 it also contains another term but it's
irrelevant for my argument right now
when I square it this gives me some time
derivative squared contains some time
derivative squared what kind of terms in
the Lagrangian involve time derivative
squared kinetic energy kinetic energy so
this is similar to the kinetic energy in
the Lagrangian of a system it's similar
to the Phi dot squared term you know the
time derivative Phi squared it's similar
to X dot squared so this is the kinetic
energy of the field now when I say
kinetic energy I just mean it contains
time derivatives squared this contains
no time derivatives the magnetic field
contains no time derivatives things
which don't contain time derivatives we
think of as
potential energy so this has the form of
kinetic energy minus potential energy
that's exactly the way lagrangian's are
supposed to look it's analogous to the
scalar field lagrangian which has five
dot squared time derivative squared
again 1/2 minus the space derivative
squared the new Lagrangian exactly the
same kind of structure time derivatives
squared minus things which don't contain
time derivatives what would you guess if
you go through the procedures of
constructing the Hamiltonian and then
the energy what would you expect the
energy or the Hamiltonian of the
electromagnetic field to be plus so the
energy in the electromagnetic field
there's just a squared plus B squared if
you work out you know if we go through
the entire apparatus of classical
mechanics and so forth we would actually
define the discover that the energy the
Hamiltonian is this and the Hamiltonian
is conserved so general principle and so
this is energy this is energy and it's
conservation a squared plus B squared is
conserved or not that rule should I say
is this the energy did I make a mistake
I did I forgot to integrate it over
space that's the energy density you
integrate it over space in other words
you account for all the degrees of
freedom at each point in space and that
becomes the energy so the integral of e
squared plus B squared over all space is
concerned it's not conserved at each
point of space energy can move from one
point of space to another
no without the integral it's the energy
density with a minus sign it's little oh
yes that's right well that that's right
with a minus sign it would be the
Lagrangian density and with a plus sign
it's the Hamiltonian density but that
just means the energy density okay now
next the equations of motion these guys
here
I'm only going to go I'm going to go
again sketch it the equations of motion
what do we do we take the Lagrangian
where do I write it I lost it all right
so it's V mu a nu minus D nu a mu times
D mu a nu minus D no angle
incidentally there and I said there was
a minus 1/4 here you can check yourself
if you leave out this term here man let
me not we just leave it the way it is
all right let me give you a piece an
example of a piece that's in here
there's a term here which is derivative
of with respect to let's say X naught a
1 minus D 1 a naught squared with a plus
with a plus with a plus 1/4 yeah
this of course is just the square of the
electric field all right let's take the
derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to D naught a 1 what is it can
you anybody differentiate this
expression with respect to this argument
here no no we want to differentiate with
respect to the derivative we want to
calculate the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to D not a 1 in
other words with respect to this
variable here right well put a 2 but the
cancels the quarter so that's 1/2
I think I've already I think this should
only be a half here there is only a half
there
so the half goes away and what else do
you get you get D naught a 1 - D 1 a
naught the derivative with respect to
this variable here how do you do it you
just differentiate the square of
something it's just the square of
something you just differentiate you get
twice - something that's it in other
words it's just F naught 1 all right
that's that's generalizable very easily
I'll write down what the general formula
is if I differentiate the Lagrangian
with receive 1 but let me write down the
general formula the derivative of the
Lagrangian with respect to the
derivative of a mu with respect to X nu
alright that is nothing but it's got a
it's got two indices mu and nu what's it
going to be what could it be
except for f mu nu and it is just like
we show that the derivative of grandjean
with respect to b naught a 1 is f naught
1 the general formula of this type is
just f mu nu now we can work out the
equation of motion what we're supposed
to do is take each one of these
derivatives here here's an example here
it is that's the formula we're using ok
we take each one of these derivatives
and differentiate it with respect to the
same index that occurs inside the
derivative over here that means D by DX
nu so the Euler Lagrange equations
just become do I have this um I think I
have it right yeah D by just a moment
let me just this is yeah I think it's
right I think I have a mistake here
let's see yeah I some index belongs
upstairs that the slower
they don't match you have a mute deaf X
when you downstairs downstairs
this is a lower index so oh so it so
yeah yeah yeah
I think it's f mu nu upstairs right this
is a lower index in the denominator so
that makes it an upper index and this is
a lower index in the denominator of a
fraction here yeah it's f nu nu both of
them upstairs okay so what's our
equation of motion differentiate with
respect to X mu F mu nu that's the
left-hand side but what's the right-hand
side it's just zero the Lagrangian
doesn't depend on the vector potential
itself so that's it which Maxwell
equations are these these are this and
this without the J I have not told you
what to do if there's a current if
there's a current the Lagrangian has to
be modified a little bit okay but
without the current how many equations
are these how many equations do I have
here
four equations four equations how many
equations do I have here one equation
and three more that's exactly what these
equations are in particular if you plug
in for F for example let's take let's
take a little piece of it let's take D
naught of F naught new
what else do we have we have plus d1 of
f1 nu plus d2 of F 2 nu plus d3 of F 3
nu like this is this is what's on the
left hand side and that's equal to 0
let's see what's there we have to pick a
new pick a new familiar which new do you
want to study okay then if we pick 0
this will be 0 because F 0 0 is 0 and
this will be d 1 of f 1 0 plus d 2 of f
2 0 plus d 3 of f 3 0
what is f 1 0 it's the first component
of the electric field so it's the
derivative of the first component of the
electric field with respect to X 1 plus
the derivative of the second component
of the electric field with respect to X
2 plus the derivative of the third
component of the electric field with
respect to X 3 this is the divergence of
the electric field right so in the
absence of charges if we don't have any
charges around any charge density that
just becomes del D equals 0 let's look
at another one let's look at let's see
we looked at the time component let's
look at the 1 component so now let's
look at a 1 component if we look at the
1 component we have derivative with
respect to time of F are not one I've
set knowing I'm setting nu equal to 1
now so the North F naught 1 plus now we
have D 1 F 1 1 but that's 0 F 1 1 is 0
and then we have plus D by DX 2 of F 2 1
plus D by DX 3 of F 3 1 I believe is
that correct I think that's correct ok
what's this term here that's the time
derivative of the electric field that's
this one what's over here well it's a
little bit complicated but what do we
have F 2 1 is B 3 so this is second
derivative the derivative with respect
to x2 of B 3 then this one if you work
it out is the other term the corresponds
to curl of B curl of B so the Euler
Lagrange equations are two of the
Maxwell equations the other two Maxwell
equations are identities they are not
equations of motion they just follow
from the definition of the electric and
magnetic field this is something you can
check I'll allow you to check it they
just follow from the fact that the
electric and magnetic fields are defined
in this way you don't have to do any
work it just follows from the structure
you've written down if you work out the
other the other components 1 + 1 + 3 1 1
3 3 yeah ok so this is an example then
that the Maxwell equations follow as the
open the Euler Lagrange equations for an
action and that same action has a
Hamiltonian that's associated with it
which is e squared plus B squared so we
have a package the package just comes
from the simple expression for the
lagrangian f mu nu squared just the the
simplest gauge invariant thing you could
have written down simple as gauge
invariant Lawrence invariant thing and
all of electromagnetism without charges
without any charges in it
all of it follows from this very simple
- a quarter well here it is - a quarter
f mu nu F mu nu okay very simple so
while you have a load of equations here
complicated it all boils down or all
derives from one simple expression for a
principle of least action if you like
alright um the last thing I'm going to
do is tell you how currents come into
this now we could just be thinking about
charged particles charged particles are
an example of a current but let's
imagine now that we have a four vector
of current J mu J mu now J mu is the
electric current in some way or another
it has to couple to the electromagnetic
field
there must be terms in the elec in the
Lagrangian which involved JMU why is
that
well where is JMU in these equations
here's the time component this is
nothing but the time component of je and
here are the space components of je here
are the space components of je over here
so J enters into the equations of motion
it must enter into the Lagrangian what
kind of simple connection what kind of
additional term in the Lagrangian can we
put in that involves je je is a vector a
for vector a for vector we've got to do
something to soak up this index what is
there around there's the vector
potential that's the only four vector
that we have to work with so let's try J
mu a mu
in other words we just take the
four-dimensional product of J with a
summit over the indices and that becomes
part of the Lagrangian of the
electromagnetic field now for all my
purposes now let's just imagine somebody
gave us the current they told us what
the current was I'm not going to get we
don't have time to study the equations
and how J varies let's just imagine
somebody told us what J is all right is
this is this is this gauge invariant so
what do you think the gauge invariant or
not we have to say something about how J
oo j oh sorry good things which are
gauge invariant are ambiguous you can
change you can change them without
changing any of the physics gauge
invariant gauge covariant form a Chinon
not physically observable things the
physical observables are the gauge
invariant quantities right so um the
electromagnetic current is a observable
quantity it's not something that changes
when you do a mathematical gauge
transformation so J is gauge invariant
it really is the flow of current you can
measure it it had better not vary when
you do a gauge transformation otherwise
it would be something which would be
ambiguous it's not ambiguous so given
that J is gauge invariant is J a gauge
invariant not obvious in fact obviously
not accept if J satisfies some special
property so let's see if the changes
when you do a gauge transformation ah
let's see where can we do this I guess
we can do it down here what happens to
j2 j AE when you gauge transformation
transform a J mu a mu will change to J
mu
a mu plus one over the electric charge
times D mu Epsilon that's the way the
vector potential changed 1 over Epsilon
in other words J mu mu changes the
change in J mu a mu is a change in J a
is J mu D mu Epsilon integral I guess
there's a 1 over electric charge so the
answer is it's not gauge invariant it
has changed by this much but then let me
do a trick the trick is called
integration by parts if you have an
integral over space or space-time oh yes
here's the integral that goes into the
action if we integrate it over
three-dimensional space it's part of the
Lagrangian if we integrate an over
four-dimensional space it becomes part
of the action the real issue is whether
the action is gauge invariant not
whether it'll Lagrangian itself if the
action is gauge invariant then the
physics will be gauge invariant all
right what do we do with this we
integrate it by parts if you integrate a
thing which is a product of one thing
times the derivative of another you can
interchange which object the derivative
acts on this is familiar with everybody
integration by parts all right it's an
identity yeah you get a surface term but
let's imagine integrating over all
space-time to calculate the action of
all space-time so assuming that very
very far away the fields and the
currents become zero
far enough away then this is equal to
minus one over e the integral of epsilon
times D mu J mu now this is the change
in this term in the action due to gauge
transformation you recognize this thing
say it again
ya be 4x d 4x but you recognize this
that's the continuity equation remember
the continuity equation the continuity
equation was the equation that said that
if a charge changes in a box the only
way it can change in the box is by
flowing through the surface of the box a
time dependence of the charge
necessarily goes with a space dependence
of the current of the space components
of the current and that we distilled
down we studied it last time and we
found out that the continuity equation
the console local conservation of charge
was exactly this equation D mu sorry D
mu J mu is equal to 0 this is also the
equation that says the time derivative
of the charge density plus the
divergence of the three-dimensional just
the usual current should be equal to 0
the only way that the charge of the
region can change is if there's a
divergence of the current which
corresponds to current flowing out of
the region out or into the region so
this equation here is d mu J mu equals 0
the continuity equation is the necessary
and sufficient condition
for the action to be gauge invariant as
long as J is a conserved for vector in
other words as long as it corresponds to
a conserved flow of electric charge the
density together with the space
component of the current then this is
gauge invariant
that's a beautiful fact that the gauge
invariance requires the current to be
conserved we didn't even use any
equation of motion for the current we
just use the fact or the assumption that
the theory was gauge invariant and from
that we derived that the continuity
equation must be true so this term which
is there if there are currents and
charges is gauge invariant under the
assumption of the continuity equation so
let's just add it in plus J mu mu now
now that it's there we will modify the
equations for the electric and magnetic
field if we go back and calculate the
equations of motion there's now a new
term that it's basically the right-hand
side here of differentiating Lagrangian
with respect to a II what if I get it
what do I get if I differentiate the
Lagrangian with respect to a II I get J
so the answer is that there is another
term on the right-hand side of the
Maxwell equations which involve the
current and charge density themselves
I'll just tell you right now that it's
this and this so if you go through this
Lagrangian workout the Euler Lagrange
equations you find some additional terms
on the right hand side which are the
current the charge density and the
current
well I'll leave that for you to do yeah
they follow just from the definition let
me give you an example okay let's check
Dell dot B equals zero now I say that we
don't need any equation of motion it
just follows from the definition of B so
let's see if we can prove that okay
let's write down the definition of the
three components of B so b3 obz I guess
when I'm going to being very specific
and working only with space components
I'll use X Y & Z BZ was DX a Y minus dy
ax right B Z X X goes to Y Y goes to Z
minus DZ a Y right and finally B what I
left out B Y XYZ v z Y X Z oops DZ a X
minus DX a Y now this is definition of B
now let's check I've made no assumption
whatever about the way that the A's are
varying in space in fact that made no
assumption because all I did was define
something okay now let's check whether
del dot B is equal to zero well why
should it be equal to zero I've made no
assumption about the way a is varying
let's check it anyway that means we have
to differentiate this with respect to Z
so let's differentiate it with this hmm
now let's check them that means we have
to take another derivative with respect
to Z and another derivative with respect
to Z here
they depend on Z
a x and y and z all depend on Z they all
depend on all the coordinates so we get
the Z the X a Y minus DZ dy a X this
means multiple derivative second
derivatives all right let's see if we
can find well let's write them all out
there and then we have to differentiate
this with respect to X that means put a
derivative with respect to X there and
another derivative with respect to X and
finally a derivative with respect to Y
here this gives us dy and this gives us
minus dy DX a Z was that it okay let's
see what we have in particular let's
track this term here this has an a Y in
it it has DZ DX a Y with a plus sign
here's another term with a why it has DZ
DX DX DZ doesn't matter which order
right opposite sign the order of another
differentiation is immaterial
and so this term and this term cancel
and so it goes let's see this let's do
one more
DZ dy ax with a minus sign dy DZ ax with
a plus sign these cancel and so it goes
all of them cancel it followed from a
definition of B the structure of B was
such by the definition B cannot be
anything if B another way of saying it
incidentally some of you may recognize
another way of saying it B is equal to
del cross a the divergence of a that
means B is the curl of a no matter what
a is it's a rule that the divergence of
a curl is equal to 0 for any a the curl
of a is B and from that it follows that
del dot B is equal to 0 so it just
follows this equation is not an equation
of motion
it's just the definition of B or a
consequence of the definition of B so is
it so is this one
consequences of the definition of B and
E definition in terms of the vector
potential that's relatively easy to
prove I won't prove it that we did it
for one of the equations you can check
out yourself that if you put in the
definitions of B&E in terms of the
vector potential that this automatically
is equal to zero contains a bunch of
terms and they all cancel out among
themselves so half of Maxwell's
equations are identities that follow
from definition and the other half are
equations of motion that follow from the
principle of least action and it is
necessary to to these equations that the
current is conserved
incidentally even if we didn't use gauge
invariance even if we didn't care about
gauge invariance but we stuck in let's
just look at something else we have the
Lagrangian which is minus 1/4 F mu nu F
mu nu and then I put in plus J dot a J
mu mu let's workout I've already worked
out what the equation of motion is that
comes just from the F mu nu terms I'll
remind you what it is it was D mu I
think F mu nu was equal to 0 that was
the equation that was how many equations
are here there are four equations here
one for each new and that was this
equation and this equation four
equations one two three four now if the
right-hand side if the if the vector
potential appears undifferentiated in a
Lagrangian that means as a right-hand
side to the Euler Lagrange equations and
what would it be it would be the
derivative of the Lagrangian with
respect to a
the result is that there will be a
right-hand side of this equation which
will be J nu here is four equations with
a right hand side which contains the
four vector of current the time
component involves the density the
charge density that's this one and the
others involve the space component
that's the other components I just
wanted to point out one thing this is
the equation of motion that followed
from adding this term to the Lagrangian
supposing I didn't know to begin with
that J has to be conserved because I
didn't know that J had to be concerned I
didn't know about all this gauge
invariance garbage and I just tried out
this term in the Lagrangian all right I
would get this equation of motion and I
would find out right now that J has to
be conserved we can check it let's just
differentiate it with respect to X mu in
other words let's take the MU of this oh
sorry D nu of it let's differentiate
with respect to X nu that would be the
continuity equation is it equal to zero
well it's equal to D nu D mu F mu nu how
about this what is this zero zero
because it contains things like d1 d2
f12 I guess it's f2 one but it also
contains d2 d1 f12 when I sum over mu
and nu I get things like D 1 D 2 F 2 1
and D 2 D 1 F 1 2 please cancel because
F 1 2 and F 2 1 this derivatives are the
same second derivative with respect to 1
and 2
F 1 2 and F 2 1 they cancel so we would
have discovered right here that the
equations of motion for F require that J
is conserved we don't really have the
option of not allowing it to be
conserved the equations of motion forces
to be conserved so there are two
independent arguments they're closely
related but nevertheless two independent
arguments one is gauge invariance we did
that nice little integration by parts
and we found out that the action was
gauge invariant if F is conserved but
even if we didn't know that the viol had
never taught us about gauge invariance
at this point we would say Maxwell's
equations this set of equations over
here is inconsistent unless unless the
current is conserved we can check it
right from here we can differentiate
this with respect to time and we can
take the divergence of some other
equation over here and we can check that
that the current will come out conserved
so that's a packaged Lagrangian of a
very simple form simplest thing we could
have written down used it doesn't mean
individually that the charge density is
conserved no and so ramona's the whole
thing
Charlie's been to some of the charge
density plus the currents the time
derivative of the charge density plus
the space derivatives the current equals
zero right now this is more than just
charge conservation it's local charge
conservation that tells us that the
charge in a region can only change if
currents are flowing into or out of that
region so it's a stronger than thing
than just saying the charge in the
universe can't change it tells us what
it says is the charge only changes in a
region by moving into and out of that
region and that's what this that's what
the continuity equation says where do we
have it we lost it well Dinu equals zero
so Maxwell's equations either in this
form or in this form immediately tell us
that the charge has to be conserved for
the Maxwell equations to make any sense
at all
well it's actually buried in this term
here and we're about finished and if we
take for the current the current
associated with a single particle and
then we also add to the Lagrangian 1/2
MV squared for that part we'll get the
Lorentz force law so we don't have time
but it's in there it's in there yeah
yeah well they're not independent of
course but yeah but right yeah that's
right so they're they're intimately tied
together and the principle of gauge
invariance of course is much more
general than just electromagnetism we
don't have time for it but it appears in
general relativity it appears
and magnetic cars wouldn't be
technologies that you're sure yeah right
so how can a tautology be wrong right
exactly
okay that's right that's right the
answer is the answer is that the right
model from monopole is the solenoid
mathematically the way mana poles are
introduced into the theory is as
infinitely long solenoid with magnetic
field going through them and coming ups
I got and so that the net divergence of
the magnetic field is zero by virtue of
the fact that what comes in goes out
it's like you know it's like a little
source of water over here yeah you know
it's like it's we have water coming into
a puddle and causing the flow of water
to diverge away from some point at the
center well if we saw that happening we
would say hey there must be a pipe
coming in somewheres okay and we account
for the water that's coming in through
the pipe and then going out away from
the pipe the divergence of the flow
would be 0 here the monopole and replace
it by the end of a long by the end of a
long solenoid right so that is the
mathematical way that that saw that the
mama poles enter into into the theory
now are there really infinitely long so
this is called a Dirac string
incidentally this is called a Dirac
string and under the right circumstances
which we won't have time for but maybe
another time this string can be
completely invisible so
[Music]
but the mathematics of it is to pretend
that the monopole were connected to a
long solenoid like this what's that
[Music]
what's that guy doing this oh I was just
thinking that that that could be the
tube black hole well not really I mean
if you surround the point is if you
surround us around the black hole or if
you surround the monopole you should see
as a net magnetic flux coming out of it
which is equal to 0 so if magnetic flux
appears to be coming into or out of the
monopole there must be a secret hidden
flow of flux away from that point and it
doesn't really matter whether this is a
black hole or anything else yeah ok
ladies and gentlemen thank you for your
attention and I will see you next next
year next year we do some general
relativity and black hole physics and
also some quantum field theory oh no way
what did we say yes and also some
statistical mechanics
general relativity in a little bit of
black holes and all those interesting
questions about about gravity which we
haven't touched on at all the quantum
mechanics of fields quantum mechanics of
fields is basically simple it just says
wherever you had a classical field now
replace it by a collection of quanta all
moving together so really that's we've
done it but there and and statistical
mechanics and thermodynamics and maybe a
little about phase transitions and
[Music]
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu